Good morning.
Today is March 22nd, it's the 24th of Adar אדר, Adar, and
today's Daf דף Daf we're starting right at the top of Nun
Tet Amud Aleph נט עמוד א, Nun Tet Amud Aleph, right where
it says Tnan תנן. Tnan. So the Mishnah משנה Mishnah had distinguished
between two different types of drainpipes from a roof. We know that
in the times of, or even modern
times in the Middle East, most of the houses have flat roofs
because they don't get so much snow,
and the problem is if you have a drainpipe, you need some
kind of a drainpipe that's going to come off of your roof
but it's going to go into your neighbor's yard. So the water
is going to spill into somebody else's yard. That's the problem in
the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, and two different types of drainpipes: Ha-marzev ein
lo chazakah המרזב אין לו חזקה, ha-marzev ein lo chazakah, a Marzev
מרזב marzev which is a more temporary type of drainpipe which we
talked about yesterday does not create a Chazakah חזקה chazakah because it
could be reoriented very easily or all different types of things or
various reasons, but a Mazcheila מזחילה, mazcheila, a more robust type of
drainpipe, yesh lo chazakah יש לו חזקה. yesh lo chazakah. So our
Gemara גמרא Gemara says: תנן המזחילה יש לו חזקה. Tnan ha-mazcheila yesh
lo chazakah. The Mazcheila מזחילה mazcheila does create a Chazakah חזקה. chazakah.
So בשלמא למאן דאמר הני תרתי שפיר אלא למאן דאמר שאם רצה
לבנות תחתיו בונה מאי נפקא ליה מינה? bishlama le-man de-amar hani tartei
shappir ela le-man de-amar she-im ratza livnot tachtav boneh mai nafka lei
mina? So there was a three-way Machlokes מחלוקת machlokes about the Marzev
מרזב, marzev, what was the reason why a Marzev מרזב marzev doesn't
have a Chazakah חזקה? chazakah? So you turn back just to yesterday's
Daf דף Daf a little bit to look. So Shmuel's שמואל Shmuel's
opinion is that מרזב אין לו חזקה מרוח אחת יש לו מקום
חזקה משתי רוחותיו. marzev ein lo chazakah mi-ruach achas yesh lo makom
chazakah mi-shtei ruchosav. So it has to do with the orientation. Rav
Hanina רב חנינא Rav Hanina amar אמר: amar: מרזב אין לו חזקה
שאם היה ארוך מקצרו. marzev ein lo chazakah she-im hayah aruch mekatzro.
If it's too long, you could shorten it, and so the length
matters. And the third opinion, אין לו מקום חזקה דאם בעי אקרי
אקרי. ein lo makom chazakah de-im ba-ei akrei akrei. So that's a
Rav Hanina רב חנינא Rav Hanina and Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba רב
ירמיה בר אבא Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba says: מרזב אין לו חזקה
שאם רצה לבנות תחתיו בונה. marzev ein lo chazakah she-im ratza livnot
tachtav boneh. You could build underneath it because it could be moved.
So it makes sense to say a Mazcheila מזחילה mazcheila does have
a Chazakah חזקה chazakah according to the first two opinions, that is
the opinion that the Marzev מרזב marzev does not create a Chazakah
חזקה chazakah because it could be reoriented, it could be moved. A
Mazcheila מזחילה mazcheila is more permanent; it can't be moved more easily.
The second opinion also makes sense because while the Marzev מרזב marzev
could be shortened, a
Mazcheila מזחילה—sorry, mazcheila thank you—a
Mazcheila מזחילה mazcheila
cannot be shortened in the same way as the Marzev מרזב. marzev.
But for the third opinion, that is the opinion of you could
build underneath it in the space underneath because—so why should that make
a difference whether it's permanent or not? So that's the Gemara's גמרא
Gemara's question. So בשלמא למאן דאמר הני תרתי שפיר אלא למאן דאמר
שאם רצה לבנות תחתיו בונה מאי נפקא ליה מינה?
bishlama le-man de-amar hani tartei shappir ela le-man de-amar she-im ratza livnot
tachtav boneh mai nafka lei mina? So what's the difference, like why
would building this Mazcheila מזחילה mazcheila create a Chazakah חזקה chazakah that
the person couldn't build underneath it in a case of a Mazcheila
מזחילה mazcheila that's a more permanent structure but not in the case
of the Marzev מרזב? marzev? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara answers: הכא
במזחילה שבבניין עסקינן. hacha be-mazcheila she-be-binyan askinan.
We're talking about a drainpipe of Mazcheila מזחילה mazcheila that is built
out of—seemingly built out of stone. That is, it is a very
permanent structure. And in such a case, therefore, not only are we
concerned that it creates a Chazakah חזקה chazakah because it's a permanent
structure, but also that any other construction that the neighbor will do,
if he builds a wall here or he does something underneath the
drainpipe, it will actually cause damage to the drainpipe if it's a
substantial form. Okay, now there is some discussion in the Rishonim ראשונים
Rishonim about: Does that mean that davka דווקא davka it has to
have been made of stone? What about other types of material? Is
it about the permanence or is it about the material? Has to
do with water damage that could be affected by the building materials
and things like that. Stone is more absorbent of water than other
things and wood. So that's a whole discussion there. De-amar lei דאמר
ליה: de-amar lei: לא ניחא לי דתיתרע אשיתאי, lo nicha li de-titra
ashitei, because I don't want the—he can say, "I don't want the
from the fact that you're building, that it's the problem of the
vibrations, basically, like we saw in the second Perek פרק, Perek, that
the building nearby is going to cause some vibration that's going to
damage the Mazcheila מזחילה." mazcheila.
Not the rest of the house?
And presumably not the rest of the house, either because
it's more protruding. So if he builds here, it's only going to
damage this, it's not going to damage the house necessarily. At least
that's the way the Rashbam רשב"ם Rashbam understands it. Rashbam רשב"ם Rashbam
says: כלומר מזחילה שלי תיפול לכל מקבת והגרזן וכל כלי ברזל בבניינך.
klomar mazcheila sheli tippol le-chol makkevet ve-ha-garzen
ve-chol kli barzel be-binyancha. If you're building a new building there, the
sound of the tools and whatever or maybe swinging the tools are
going to damage the Mazcheila מזחילה.
mazcheila. Sounds like if you make a shed underneath it, it won't
be some big undertaking.
So it depends. Any kind of a binyan בניין binyan that's going
to have some impact on the Mazcheila מזחילה—obviously mazcheila each case is
going to—I mean, how do you draw the distinction between a Marzev
מרזב marzev and a Mazcheila מזחילה mazcheila is also part of the
issue here as well, which is that it has to do with—
How permanent is a structure and how easily damaged.
So it could be that in any of these cases in the
end the assessment really has to be based on how the דיינים
dayanim see the reality of the case. But these are just sort
of initial guidelines.
What do those words literally mean? קטרא דצובא kitra detzuva like from
the, like the
קטרא kitra like to become weak.
רעוע, raua, right? רעוע raua and אשיטי? ashitai?
אשיטי ashitai from the, if I remember correctly the phrase,
now I’m trying to remember back, I think it was in the
second פרק perek the same phrase came up around the time of
the, around the, by the, the from the tools, something like that.
But there was a discussion there that it was about the vibration
or about the noise from the, from the work will damage the
building. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: צינור
המקלח מים לחצר חברו. Tzinor hamekaleach mayim lachatzer chaveiro. This is an
interesting situation. So you have a drainpipe that connects, collects the water
from the roof and carries it into somebody else's yard. Okay, צינור
מקלח מים לחצר חברו, Tzinor hamekaleach mayim lachatzer chaveiro, ובא בעל הגג
לסתמו. uba ba'al hagag lisatmo. The roof owner, that is the house
owner here, wants to plug up the drainpipe. He wants to make
a different drainpipe, he decided he wanted to do some renovations, so
he plugs up the drainpipe. Okay.
Now normally we would think in most cases water coming from the
roof is actually something that is damaging to the lower field. That's
why there's a whole question, does it create a חזקה? chazakah? Is
your having a drainpipe here something whose presence actually has an impact
and you can assume the consent of the other party? So ובא
בעל הגג לסתמו בעל החצר מעכב עליו. uba ba'al hagag lisatmo ba'al
hachatzer me'akeiv alav. In fact, the field owner can request that he
please reopen the drainpipe. He's allowed to. Why? He wants the water.
דאמר ליה כי היכי דאת קנית לך חצר דידי למשדי ביה מיא
לדידי נמי קני לי מיא דאגרך.
De'amar lei ki heichi de'at kanit lach chatzer didi lemishdi bei maya
lididi
nami kani li maya de'agrach. When you as if, quote-unquote, bought my
field for the purpose of dumping your water there, I bought the
rights to the water from your roof. As the רשב"ם Rashbam says,
it's actually almost like a real official business deal. The רשב"ם Rashbam
says, sorry I'm just trying to find the
line, ודמי למקח וממכר. vedami lemakach umimkar. It could be after the
three years.
Not, until three years there’s no חזקה chazakah anyway.
But it's not about the חזקה chazakah at this point. It's actually
just that the moment, so if you look in the רשב"ם, Rashbam,
רשב"ם Rashbam דיבור המתחיל לדידי נמי קני לי מיא דאגרך,
dibur hamatchil lididi nami kani li maya
de'agrach, ולהשקות בהמתאי, ulhashkot beheimtai, I want to water my animals, שעל
מנת כן נתרציתי לך. she'al minat kein nitratzeiti lach. The reason why
I until now have not objected, which is why I think it
could even be less than three years, that is until now, the
reason I've consented to this is to because it actually benefits me.
ודמי למקח וממכר. vedami lemakach umimkar. It's like an actual purchase. שאני
שיעבדתי לך חצרי בשביל מימך. she'ani shibadeti lach chatzeri bishvil meimecha. I
have subjugated my property rights to you in exchange for the water
rights. So that is, this has become a mutually beneficial situation where
the water from the drainpipe spills into the animal trough for the
animals to drink, and then the, therefore if the roof owner wants
to plug up the drainpipe, it's actually now,
it's
some kind of גזילה gezeilah because they've as if made this exchange.
He gave up his property rights for the water rights, and now
you want to deny him the water rights that, you can't renege
on that deal without his consent.
That does, it's so much circumscribed though the renovations he can do.
Exactly, so that’s part of this question that gets brought
up in the נימוקי יוסף Nimukei Yosef on the רי"ף, Rif, there's
a bit of a מחלוקת machlokes in the ראשונים Rishonim about how
far does this go. Does it totally, too long I can't find
the citation. Basically the נימוקי יוסף Nimukei Yosef himself disagrees with the
ר"ה. Ra'ah. The ר"ה Ra'ah seems to say that it would limit
the types of renovations but only to specific types of things. נימוקי
יוסף Nimukei Yosef seems to understand that it would actually limit the
renovations very, very expansively, even to the extent that perhaps he can't
add a second story and things like that because it's going to
deny the water right. And you sort of have to think, well
how formal was this agreement? They never said anything to each other,
it’s totally implicit. The רשב"ם Rashbam says דמי למקח וממכר, dami lemakach
umimkar, it’s similar to a purchase, but how far does that really
go and what kind of a claim would he actually have in
court if it would come up in that case? You know the
ruling is בעל החצר מעכב עליו. ba'al hachatzer me'akeiv alav. He can
object and he can insist that he leave open the water pipe.
But what if he just builds a different roof that just totally
stops the flow of water?
He can object as long as there's a water pipe. Right.
If there's no water pipe at all or if the total situation
has changed.
Demolish the house.
All sorts of things. So it’s a fascinating
example.
Yeah, that's Rav אהרן הלוי. Aaron Halevi.
Yeah, so the contemporary of the ריטב״א, Ritva, and the נמוקי יוסף
Nimukei Yosef was a student of the ריטב״א, Ritva, but since the
ריטב״א Ritva himself is a student or contemporary student of the רא״ה,
Ra'ah, so many of his teachings that Spanish school, yeah. Okay, דבישי
ליה להאי לא לידייניה מהאי קבילו ליה. De-bish lay leh-hai lo li-dayneh
meh-hai kabilu leh. Okay, מאי דאגרא. mai de-agra. So איתמר, Itmar, רבי
אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. So רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya said אמר מעכב. amar
me'akev.
רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya ruled that he could object in this case
of the drain pipe. רבי חמא Rabbi Chama אמר אינו מעכב. amar
eino me'akev. רבי חמא, Rabbi Chama, you should know, רבי חמא Rabbi
Chama is the son of רבי
אושעיא.
Rabbi
Oshaya.
רבי חמא'ס Rabbi Chama's the father? I thought רבי חמא Rabbi Chama
was the son.
I'm just telling you what it says here, רבי חמא'ס Rabbi Chama's
the father of רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya.
Oh, you're right.
I looked in תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, sorry, my mistake. Okay, so רבי
חמא Rabbi Chama is the father of רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. He's
quoted after him interestingly. אמר אינו מעכב. Amar eino me'akev. He says
that you cannot object, that is presumably he doesn't hold of this
mutually beneficial implicit type of agreement as being binding. So אזל שייליה
לרבי ביסא. Azal shailei le-Rabbi Bisa. So then the case came to
רבי ביסא, Rabbi Bisa, who is the son of רבי אושעיא. Rabbi
Oshaya. So we have three generations in the same family dealing with
the same case. So the case came to רבי ביסא, Rabbi Bisa,
אמר להו מעכב. amar lehu me'akev. And he, רבי ביסא, Rabbi Bisa,
ruled like his father, not like his grandfather. So קרי ליה kari
leh רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama והחוט המשולש לא במהרה ינתק.
ve-hachut hameshulash lo bimehera yinatek. רמי
בר חמא Rami bar Chama quoted about this family the פסוק pasuk
from קהלת Kohelet that a threefold string, a string made from three
strands will not break so easily. Most strings are made out of
doubling, out of the two strands, so a stronger woven strand would
be even stronger. And that's the idea of the six... the משכן
mishkan had all different kinds of eightfold and sixfold and all kinds
of things. So here the assessment is that in a family where
you have three generations of תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, that's a really
wonderful thing, that the third generation already is showing a great strength
in learning. And that's זה רבי אושעיא בנו של רבי חמא בנו
של רבי ביסא. zeh Rabbi Oshaya beno shel Rabbi Chama beno shel
Rabbi Bisa. That's רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya who's himself the son of
רבי חמא Rabbi Chama who's the son of רבי ביסא. Rabbi Bisa.
So it goes back all the way that רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya
agreed with his grandfather's opinion but not with his father's. רבי ביסא
Rabbi Bisa is the grandfather, right.
Oh, whoa, so that's even better because a grandson, right, right.
So תוספות Tosafot says I don't understand, there are all sorts of
families where there are three generations of rabbis. So look in תוספות,
Tosafot, החוט
המשולש לא במהרה ינתק, hachut hameshulash lo bimehera yinatek, כמה הוו שהם
דאבותיהם דאבות אבותיהם היו תלמידי חכמים. kama havu she-hem de-avoteihem de-avot avoteihem
hayu talmidei chachamim. There are many
generations where there are three generations
of rabbis.
רבן גמליאל'ס Rabban Gamliel's family for example,
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי.
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. So you have many amazing... many of these
families had great תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim for many generations, so I
don't understand. ולא קאמר עליהם החוט המשולש. velo ka'amar aleihem hachut hameshulash.
רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama did not quote this פסוק pasuk
about any of them. אלא הכא, ela hacha, except in this case,
היינו טעמא לפי ששלשתן ראו זה את זה, hainu ta'ama lefi she-shloshtan
ra'u zeh et zeh, because each of them, not only were they
three generations of Torah scholars, they were three generations of Torah scholars
who interacted, who were able to have a rich מחלוקת machloket between
them, who were operative during the same generation. That is, רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya was alive while his grandfather was also still alive and
they were both learning and פסקנינג paskening and teaching together, they could
have that dialogue.
So that never presents problems?
I'm sure, I'm sure it presents problems, but I meaning, meaning when
there's a debate within the family. Yeah, of course I can imagine
all sorts of cases where that could be a problem and then
you have to deal with, you know in general in פסק, psak,
we usually say if it's a מחלוקת machloket between a father and
a son, usually you פסקן pasken like the father in the גמרא
Gemara because of there's a sense that the son should have learned
the opinions from his father, the father carries more authoritative weight, but
then we have הלכתא כבתראי, hilchata ke-batrai, the later opinions carry more
weight, so there are all these different dynamics at play,
and you know you can imagine the son goes to learn in
someone else's ישיבה yeshiva or has another teacher besides his father and
then there are enriched and expanded dynamics in that way. Very often,
you know as much as you grow up with a certain upbringing
you can also reject your parent's upbringing as well, so how do
you balance all of those things is important, and but just the
beauty also of thinking about the grandparent relationship with children and there
are all discussions there not only about the parent's obligation to educate
their children but also grandparents have an obligation to support the education
of their children, either to learn together or to spend money towards
it, so there's a lot to go into further there as well.
Okay, the משנה mishnah continues going from drain pipes into ladders. So
the משנה mishnah had contrasted
סולם המצרי sulam hamitzri a...
So
you have a ladder here, right, going up to your roof.
So the ladder, the ladder goes into somebody else's yard. That's basically
the problem. So the משנה Mishnah had said סולם המצרי Sulam HaMitzri
אין לו חזקה, ein lo chazakah, an Egyptian ladder does not create
a חזקה. chazakah. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What are we talking about
סולם המצרי? Sulam HaMitzri? What is an Egyptian ladder? אמר רבי ינאי,
Amar Rabbi Yannai, כל שאין לו ארבעה שלביקין. kol she-ein lo arba’ah
shalvikin. Anything that doesn’t have four rungs. The ladder I drew has
four rungs, so if you erase one, then it only has three
rungs. So that’s a סולם המצרי. Sulam HaMitzri.
So what’s a סתם סולם? stam sulam?
A סתם סולם stam sulam presumably you’d have to go and see.
I’m not sure why an Egyptian ladder is so short or why
a Tyrian ladder is so tall. Probably has something to say about
it.
A step stool.
A step stool? Short ladder or to go up to the shelf,
but not to go up to the roof, or it’s very weak.
Step ladder. Step ladder, all different kinds of things. Anyway, so the
reason why it doesn’t create a חזקה chazakah is because it’s so
temporary. It’s a weaker kind of a ladder, so that’s why its
presence on the property doesn’t assume that the owner has granted property
rights based on that. Okay, and now the משנה Mishnah had continued,
not only from ladders, now we talk about windows, going back to
the first beginning of the מסכת masechet about היזק ראיה, hezek re’iyah,
windows and building walls and all sorts of things like that. So
the משנה Mishnah says:
חלון המצרי אין לו חזקה, Chalon HaMitzri ein lo chazakah. ולצורי יש
לו חזקה. u'l-Tzuri yesh lo chazakah. An Egyptian window does not create
a חזקה chazakah and the Tyrian window does. Now I can’t imagine
there’s some connection between the windows and the ladders, but I don’t
know enough about the construction practices to be able to figure it
out right now.
But
I mean a window’s not portable, but it certainly is separate.
Right, but the idea is that the window, if the window, so
we’re going to see, but the discussion of the window is that
there’s a problem of היזק ראיה, hezek re’iyah, that the neighbors will
be able to see each other, the privacy. Right. So the גמרא
Gemara says, חלון המצרי Chalon HaMitzri אין לו חזקה. ein lo chazakah,
Why does an Egyptian window not create a חזקה? chazakah? מאי שנא
גבי סולם דלא מפרש ומאי שנא גבי חלון דמפרש? Mai shna gabei
sulam d'la mefareish u'mai shna gabei chalon d'mefareish? And the משנה Mishnah
goes on, even in the משנה, Mishnah, to explain: איזהו היא חלון
המצרי? Eizehu hi chalon hamitzri? What is an Egyptian window? כל שאין
ראשו של אדם יכול ליכנס לתוכה. Kol she-ein rosho shel adam yachol
likaneis l'tochah. An Egyptian window is so small a person can’t put
their head, so presumably, you know, something like this size, maybe a
טפח, tefach, טפח tefach and a half width, something like that. A
person’s head can’t fit through the hole. So what’s the difference there?
Why does the משנה Mishnah tell us the difference between windows but
not by ladders? That’s the גמרא’s Gemara question. מאי שנא גבי סולם
דלא מפרש ומאי שנא גבי חלון דמפרש? Mai shna gabei sulam d'la
mefareish u'mai shna gabei chalon d'mefareish? משום דקבעי איפלוגי רבי יהודה
בסיפא.
Mishum d'kaba’ei iplugi Rabbi
Yehuda b'seifa.
Maybe? Maybe they knew it better and so on.
Maybe. Alternatively, there’s no, the way the גמרא Gemara understands it, since
there’s no debate about the ladders, it’s a less relevant fact. Because
there’s a מחלוקת machloket about something, you have to be more specific
in explicating what’s the case. So the גמרא Gemara says: משום דקבעי
איפלוגי רבי יהודה בסיפא. Mishum d'kaba’ei iplugi Rabbi Yehuda b'seifa. Since Rabbi
Yehuda disagrees about what kind of window qualifies as a חלון המצרי
chalon hamitzri or not. Rabbi Yehuda says: אם יש לה מלבן אף
על פי שאין ראשו של אדם יכול ליכנס לתוכה הרי זה חזקה.
Im yesh lah malben af al pi she-ein rosho shel adam yachol
likaneis l'tochah harei zeh chazakah. So he says even a smaller window
could still create a חזקה, chazakah, so you need the distinction in
the משנה Mishnah in order to be able to support the fact
of Rabbi Yehuda being able to disagree. I’m reminded of a comment
of the רשב"ם, Rashbam, why does when the sons of נח Noach
leave the ark, it says וחם הוא אבי כנען. v'Cham hu avi
Chanaan. So like why is that relevant? The פשט pshat it doesn’t
make any sense, okay, so okay, so Cham was the father of
Canaan, who cares? It’s a pasuk later. So later, because the discussion
of when נח Noach gets undressed, we have to know why נח
Noach is cursing חם Cham later, because חם Cham is the descendant
of, because כנען Chanaan is the son of חם. Cham. So we
would never have had that context to understand why נח Noach is
cursing him unless we already knew that כנען Chanaan was the son
of חם. Cham. So it’s a setup. You have to have that
detail going in in order for the story to make sense.
So here too, as the story does never curse Cham, but curses
Chanaan.
That’s exactly the point, why is it mentioned there?
No, but separate from that, in the narrative.
Oh it says it again? It says it again. Well, go read
the רשב"ם Rashbam there. רש"י Rashi obviously brings a מדרש midrash which
has a more rich description of why כנען Chanaan was punished as
well. Okay,
so משום דאיפלוגי רבי יהודה בסיפא. mishum d'iplugi Rabbi Yehuda b'seifa. אמר
רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, למטה מארבע אמות יש לו חזקה. lemata
m’arba amot yesh lo chazakah. Rabbi Zeira says even a small window,
if it’s below ארבע אמות, arba amot, that is below a person’s
height, that is where a person could actually see through the window
without getting on a ladder, then that would create a חזקה chazakah
even a very small window. You can imagine for people’s privacy, even
a small window is going to be damaging, והיזק ראיה. v'hezek re’iyah.
And you could object, ולמעלה מארבע אמות אין לו חזקה ואינו חלון.
u’l-ma’alah m’arba amot ein lo chazakah v’eino chalon. So Rabbi Zeira says
it’s all about the height seemingly.
Why למטה מארבע אמות יש לו חזקה? lemata m’arba amot yesh lo
chazakah?
Because if it’s below ארבע אמות, arba amot, if it’s down here,
then you can have somebody looking through the window. Right?
So you have to assume
that the whole reason we care about that.
If it's a window very high up, so no one can see
through the window, so there's no חזקה chazakah there. There's no problem
of היזק ראייה hezek re'iyah for a high window according to רבי
זירא. Rabbi Zeira. And that goes back to all of those questions
about היזק ראייה hezek re'iyah and the requirement that when you want
to build a wall out of היזק ראייה hezek re'iyah problems, the
wall always had to be ארבע אמות, arba amot, ארבע אמות arba
amot more or less the height above which is taller than the
average person, so therefore it would prevent any type of peeping and
things like that. Okay.
So that means if there's אין לו חזקה ein lo chazakah that
means at any point, like ten years later, the next-door neighbor can
say move your top story window?
Right, it means at any point because—so not the top story window,
'cause it's too tall—but if he has a first floor window, a
first floor window you could object whenever you want. אין לו חזקה.
ein lo chazakah. Even after three years you can't say well you
never objected to it before. Say no, I decided now that I
want to have more privacy, I want to, you know, I or
I changed my routine, whatever it is, you have a reasonable reason
to object to that window being there.
Okay, so when we say יש לו חזקה, yesh lo chazakah, it
means in three
years—within three years
the neighbor can object.
The neighbor can object, and after three years you can't object.
And what about as opposed to a top one where we can
never object?
No, the top one, right, the top one you can never object
because you have no reason to be concerned here.
There's no problem. Wouldn't you say it's even worse because then he's
higher up, he can see more of the guy's yard?
No, but he can't get up there.
What do you mean he can't get up there? You don't... people
don't have a second floor?
No, but the reason you would have a window this tall is
not to be able to see out of, but it's to let
light in or to let fresh air in.
And let's say
there was a second story?
Does that make it different?
Presumably not. The problem—'cause again, right, when we talk about all these
things of walls and things, it's always just an assumption that it's
ארבע אמות. arba amot. ארבע אמות arba amot is like the, the
rule.
Wait, maybe I'm confused. Like if you have a second story with—if
you have the high window. Yes. So if I am the neighbor
not in that house, yes, and I want to build my house
two stories tall. Yeah. Okay. So the first guy can require me
to build a wall so that I can't look out my window
into his room.
Right, 'cause you have a big, a two-story house.
Exactly. So I'm the purple—the purple man can require the green man
to build
for a wall here
so that he can't look into my window.
Onto your roof, really.
Right. Now what I don't understand is, if that's the case, right,
that's the case.
That's not our case.
That's not our case. Our case only concerned with the lower window.
The lower, the windows in this house.
But it's the same principle. Yeah, something like that. Why can't—why doesn't
the Talmud ever say, Listen, I'm building my green house. I'm gonna
have it three stories, I don't want a wall. Put up a
blind. Put up a Venetian blind. Put up a curtain.
Put up a shutter. So that's part of the מחלוקת machloket we've
had in בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, which is the whole question of
על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו al hanizak leharichik et atzmo or המזיק.
hamazik. Thanks. Would you say that in
English for people like...
Whose responsibility is it to distance themselves from the damage? In certain
types of damage, it's actually the responsibility of the ניזק, nizak, the
person getting damaged.
Usually it's—we would say the responsibility is on the מזיק, mazik, the
one who does the damage, right. So that becomes a question of
some of these more ephemeral types of damage like היזק ראייה, hezek
re'iyah, privacy problems, or in case of like an oven that makes
too much smoke and things like that. We had a whole מחלוקת
machloket about
the דבורים devorim and the and the.
So
then what Tova is saying is correct, that if you put up
a blind or a shade or a
shutter, whose responsibility is it? Is it—is it the responsibility of the
person who lives here to block his windows or is it the
person—the responsibility... does he have to pay for the wall or is
it this person's responsibility that if you don't want someone to peep
into your yard, you should build the wall? Those kinds of questions
we've had throughout the whole מסכת. masechet. So it's really about and
more broadly, obviously, this is about how do you live with your
neighbors. Sometimes who do you compromise with? Whose responsibility is it, everything
like that. Okay. Fine. So that's the opinion of רבי זירא. Rabbi
Zeira. So that's the opinion of רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira says למטה מד' אמות יש לו חזקה. lematah miedalet amot
yesh lo chazakah. If it's below ארבע אמות, arba amot, it can
create a חזקה chazakah because the assumption is you would have objected
in the first three years. יכול למחות. yachol limchot. למעלה מד' אמות
אין לו חזקה. lema'alah miedalet amot ein lo chazakah. If it's above
ארבע אמות, arba amot, אין לו חזקה ein lo chazakah but also
אינו יכול למחות. eino yachol limchot. You can't object to it because
there's nothing to object about it. If it's above ארבע אמות, arba
amot, the assumption is that you can't cause any, any vision problem.
And obviously in this case, we're really talking just about two houses
that are next to each other. That is two one-story houses. We're
not talking... so the question is whether this window can peep into
this house, but this window, no one, no one is that high
up.
Why do you assume that people aren't that high up?
Because people are only five feet tall.
No, but honestly, there's no multi-story houses?
In this case, the case that we're talking about where ארבע אמות
arba amot makes sense is when there's only one story. If it's
a second story, then you need another ארבע אמות arba amot to
counterbalance the height of the next story. That would be
my.
Okay, so that's the opinion of רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. Okay. ורבי
אילא אמר אפילו למעלה מארבע אמות אין לו חזקה בחלון המצרי. veRabbi
Ila amar afilu lemala mearba amot ein lo hazakah be'chalon hamitzri. רבי
אילא Rabbi Ila says even if it's above ארבע אמות, arba amot,
the high window does not create a חזקה hazakah because he always
retains the right to object, the neighbor. So the גמרא Gemara says
לימא בכופין על מדת סדום קמיפלגי, leima bechofin al midat S'dom kamiflagi,
maybe they disagree about whether or not the court can enforce what
we call מדת סדום. midat S'dom. Right? That is something which is
detrimental to one person but not really beneficial to one another person.
So in this case, right, having this high
window, something which is
beneficial to one—sorry, right—and the detriment is very minimal. Right, so here
he has this window that he wanted to have in his house,
there's a relatively minimal detriment being caused to his neighbor, and nonetheless
does the court still impose on him to get rid of the
window? Okay, so גמרא Gemara סבר כופין s'var chofin ומר סבר אין
כופין, u'mar savar ein chofin, maybe the מחלוקת machloket between רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira and רבי אילא Rabbi Ila is whether or not the
court can force him to block up the window. And the גמרא
Gemara says לא דכולי עלמא כופין. lo dekulei alma chofin. Everyone agrees
that the court is empowered to impose in cases of מדת סדום,
midat S'dom, ושני הכא דאמרי ליה זימנין דמותבת
שרשיפא תותך וקיימת וחזית.
ve'shani hacha de'amrei
lei zimnin demotva sharshifa tutach vekayamt vechazit. So maybe like he's saying,
what Michael suggested, that there's an assumption maybe in the high window
there's a concern that you'll actually come to stand on a שרשיפא
sharshifa or something like that, and that's the problem rather than that
the high window—saying oh, a high window doesn't cause any damage at
all. Actually maybe the debate is how much of a damage the
high window really has. One, רבי אילא Rabbi Ila is concerned that
a person could stand on a שרשיפא, sharshifa, steps-stool and peep out
through the top window or something like that. And רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira is less concerned for that reality. Okay.
ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבי אמי.
hahu de'ata
kimei deRabbi Ami.
We implied that if there really was a second story, everyone would
agree that there is real damage and you
could—which is what I was trying to say before, that in any
case of a second story you would need to have a corresponding
second story or another wall. Right,
so that's why you have to follow the narrative flow of the
גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara now brings a real case. ההוא
דאתא לקמיה דרבי אמי. hahu de'ata kimei deRabbi Ami. שרשיפא? sharshifa?
That's like a little stool, right?
שרשיפא sharshifa like a stool. I think the
רשב"ם Rashbam says ספסל. safsal. Like a bench, a stool, something like
that. Okay.
So someone came in a court case to רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami.
שדריה לקמיה דרבי אבא בר ממל, shadrei lekamei deRabbi Abba bar Memel,
and he sent him to רבי אבא בר ממל. Rabbi Abba bar
Memel. So אמר ליה עביד ליה כרבי אילא, amar lei avi lei
keRabbi Ila, and he told him you should פסקן pasken in this
case like רבי אילא. Rabbi Ila. That is even a high-level window
we're concerned that someone will be peeping out through the window because
they would stand on a stool. אמר שמואל. amar Shmuel. So שמואל's
Shmuel opinion as a follow-up to that, that is, the conclusion of
the סוגיא sugya seems to be so far, פסקן pasken like רבי
אילא, Rabbi Ila, that is even a high window we are concerned
about because היזק ראיה, hezek re'iyah,
there's these concerns that you would stand on a stool.
And even by the way for a small window, because that was
the whole discussion that got us into it. That is, a small
window we're less concerned that you'll be looking out through because you
can't put your head through the window, it's too small. So שמואל
Shmuel gets the last word. אמר שמואל ולאורה אפילו כל שהוא יש
לו חזקה. amar Shmuel ule'ora afilu kol shehu yesh lo hazakah. If
it's made for light, that is, it's clear that the window is
not for the purpose of looking out of or putting your laundry
out of or anything like that. It really is just to let
light into what's otherwise a very dark building. Like this building. Maybe
a skylight. It's a skylight maybe, or it's—this building has no windows
except for this one. So it's very clear that the purpose is
to let in the light from the sun, or it's a very
dim area. Therefore, the assumption is not that the person will be
looking out of the window because the window serves a functional purpose
for the building. So שמואל Shmuel says ולאורה, ule'ora, if it's to
provide light for the room, אפילו כל שהוא, afilu kol shehu, even
a very small window, יש לו חזקה. yesh lo hazakah. After three
years you lose the right to object because at that point the
assumption is that that's an integral part of how the structure was
made. You should have objected earlier if you had a problem with
it.
So let me ask you this. Let's say that's the situation and
the person who has his house sells it to someone else.
Does the three years start again? In other words, because maybe the
person who now owns the house has a different view of what
he wants to do with that window.
Presumably, my guess would be that Talmudic times, the windows that are
made for light had—it was clear that it was made for light.
I think the assumption if you look in the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the
assumption is that it's based on the context. That is, this is
a dark room or it's a dark area, the alleyway is very
dim, something like that.
But isn't it possible that a window could be used for two
different purposes depending
on the nature of an individual? Certainly.
Right. If a רבי rabbi can say a שרשיפא, sharshifa, obviously that's
right. nature of an individual? Certainly. Right.
I mean if the rabbi could say a stepstool, obviously that's the
way they're thinking. It gets bit dicey because then how do you
count the חזקה chazakah years? Presumably you would go by the original
owner because it's based on the physical structure of the building and
so that would be used up, but like you're saying, if it
has some kind of more flexible use and you maybe it got
switched from use in one way or he wanted to expand the
window or something like that, I would think you would have to
take some action actually to restart the count. That would be my
sense. He would have to open the window more or do something
because otherwise he just bought the property as is and moves in.
Why should it restart the years for the חזקה? chazakah? That would
be my gut feel.
Yes, just on that.
It's not smooth for me. If the assumption is it's so small
that it's structural for light, and the assumption is he's not going
to be looking out at that, why should there be the opportunity
for a מחאה mecha'ah within those three years?
Because there's still the concern, right psychologically, this person is still even
if there's no real risk that this person is going to look
out the window, this person is nervous or worried that this person
is looking out their window.
That's an interesting thing. In other words, we'll say we know it's
for light. There's no real assumption he's going to peep through the
window and look.
But if you're worried about it or if it bothers you, you
have to let him know by three years.
But we're still going to legally allow you to act on the
potential anxiety you might have or discomfort, that's even weaker. Your discomfort
is strong enough to make him remove the window within three years.
Right.
And the רשב''ם Rashbam just points out the other reason you might
want a window is to be able to oversee your properties and
things like that. To look out is very different than to be
able to let light in. You can imagine a very small window
or something like that is less practical for that. Okay. The משנה
Mishnah continues. הזיז עד טפח. Haziz ad tefach. What is a זיז?
ziz? A זיז ziz is as the רשב''ם Rashbam says, מי שיש
לו כותל סמוך לחצר חבירו והוציא זיז טפח בולט מכותלו לחצר חבירו.
Mi sheyesh lo kotel samuch lechatzer chaveiro vehotzi ziz tefach bolet mikotlo
lechatzer chaveiro.
It's like a protrusion. So let's redraw our picture here a little
bit. So we have a house and we have a חצר chatzer
and there's another house over here, right? This guy has a house
also. Okay, fine. Very good. It's all cubes, right? Okay, so this
is, he's got the door here.
In next life, you'll be an architect.
Exactly. Okay, so this is the חצר chatzer here. Now this person
has a protrusion, like a little,
like a block, a ledge, a ledge, a little small ledge, very
small. So the משנה Mishnah says, הזיז עד טפח יש לו חזקה.
Haziz ad tefach yesh lo chazakah.
If it's up to one טפח tefach wide, very small kind of
a ledge, then it does have a חזקה, chazakah, that is you
have up to three years to object and afterwards it gets to
stay, and ויכול למחות. veyachol limchot.
And the other person who owns the חצר, chatzer, right, this חצר
chatzer doesn't belong to him. His door is over here. So his
חצר chatzer is somewhere over here. This is your neighbor's yard. So
your neighbor could object to you having this protrusion. Why? Why would
he want this? I want to hang my skis here. I want
to hang up my
bicycle
hook, something like this, or
I want to have a structure that enables you in the future
to
build a מרפסת mirpeseit or something like that. I could put a
flower pot, anything like that.
So the neighbor, if he wants to object, has to object within
three years. Okay. If it's פחות מטפח, pachot mitefach, if it's smaller
than one טפח, tefach, אין לו חזקה. ein lo chazakah. It is
too small to create a חזקה, chazakah, that is even after three
years, he could still object. Sorry, it doesn't acquire me the right
to this use even after three years because it's so
small, but ואינו יכול למחות. veaino yachol limchot. Because it's so small,
the property owner here also can't object. So it's kind of a
tradeoff. If it's large enough to create a חזקה chazakah after three
years, it's also something that could be objected to. If it's so
small that it will never create a חזקה chazakah anyway, so then
there's also no room for him to object or to require you
to destroy it. Yes, so.
So the relevance of whether there is or isn't a חזקה chazakah
if the overriding rule is that the other guy can't object?
So if he can't object, it still would create, so the point
is אין לו חזקה ein lo chazakah that is I can't now
go and renovate this or expand it or take the space that's
reserved for it to use for something else because this entire property
belongs to him.
That's the argument. That is אין לו חזקה ein lo chazakah means
I never, I would never own this extra piece even after three
years, even after ten years, whatever. It's so small that it has
no legal standing.
Even though you possess that extra piece? That wouldn't say anything about
if you decided to take that down and
build a much larger shelf. Then of course he can object. But
just the use, about the use of this small space, that is
it's never really transferred ownership. It always remains this person's ownership.
You understand? There's... רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov אמר רבי מני Amar Rabbi
Mani so
there is two different versions quoted in the name of רבי מני:
Rabbi Mani: החזיק בטפח החזיק בארבע. Hechezik be-tefach hechezik be-arba. If you
create a חזקה chazakah of one טפח, tefach, then that allows you
then to have a חזקה chazakah up to four טפחים, tefachim, a
wider ledge. That is once you have built a smaller ledge that
does create a חזקה, chazakah, and that I think goes back to
Gloria, your question, that is if it is so small that it
would not create the חזקה, chazakah, then it is small enough that
you could never expand it. But if it is large enough to
create even a small חזקה, chazakah, it is large enough to have
established ownership, then at that point then you could imagine renovating it
to be a larger ledge later. And the significance of all these
measurements is quite interesting. Something that I think about a lot across
שס Shas is how much do the שיעורים, shiurim, the measurements, translate
from context to context. So here, for example, four טפחים tefachim is
the minimum size of a space with significance for הלכות שבת. Hilchot
Shabbat. Anything smaller than four טפחים tefachim does not count as an
independent רשות reshut for carrying on שבת. Shabbat.
What would you just tell me four טפחים?
tefachim? One טפח tefach is around three to four inches, so four
טפחים tefachim is somewhere between a foot and 16 inches. So, you
know, like the size of this גמרא Gemara is like a reasonable
estimation of a significant area. That is, I could put something here,
I could put my mail here, something like that. But if it
is smaller than that, it is a space which lacks significance as
a space, as an independent space. So that has important ramifications for
carrying on הלכות שבת. Hilchot Shabbat. If I have a space that
is so small, like the top of a post or or the
top of a mailbox or something like that, that is so small,
then you could carry onto that. It is called מקום פטור mekom
patur because it is so small that it lacks significance. So here
too we have similar measurements: one טפח tefach wide, four טפחים tefachim
wide, things like that. Other significant terminology, חזל Chazal obviously had a
certain understanding of certain sizes were universal measurements that were applicable to
many different contexts. So these are just interesting to think about when
we see those.
Just one thing, go back to your diagram for a second. So
the whole discussion about the חלונות, chalonot, all of a sudden it
is, why is the חלונות, chalonot, why did you put it on
that wall? It has something to do with
that was a initial version of the ledge,
should be on the other wall, right?
Well, in this case, right, it would be in this wall.
I just wanted to make sure.
It was a bad picture to start off. I have improved the
picture over time. Okay. For a different case. So now we are
talking about ledges. So רבי מני's Rabbi Mani position is החזיק בטפח
החזיק בארבע. Hechezik be-tefach hechezik be-arba. If you had a חזקה chazakah
established for a one טפח tefach wide זיז, ziz, then by the
time you could even expand it later into four טפחים. tefachim. מאי
קאמר? Mai ka'amar? אמר אביי Amar Abaye הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. What
is he talking about? So אביי Abaye says הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar:
החזיק רוחב טפח במשך ארבע. hechezik rochav tefach be-meshech arba. If you
had created a חזקה chazakah of רוחב טפח, rochav tefach, a width
of one טפח tefach במשך ארבע, be-meshech arba, so it is four
long and one wide. And this is the wall, right? Then אביי
Abaye says החזיק ברוחב ארבע. hechezik be-rochav arba. Then you could expand
it to four, sorry, one second. אמר אביי הכי קאמר החזיק רוחב
טפח במשך ארבע החזיק ברוחב ארבע. Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar hechezik rochav
tefach be-meshech arba hechezik be-rochav arba. Then once you have established the
חזקה chazakah in this property for three years, you could come along
later and expand so that it is four טפחים tefachim wide. That
is you could make the ledge basically that
is
a ledge, an overhang, that is what you are drawing.
Initial question that we might have thought it was talking about was
if you had a one by one something like that and now
you want to expand it this
way, length-wise. But that seems in this case to be not what
is being talked about. So אביי, Abaye, this is אביי's Abaye position,
that is once you have created a space one by four, you
could expand it to four by four. But if it was smaller,
if it was one by however much, you do not get to
then create all both directions. You can not expand two-dimensionally. Like if
it was only here for the חזקה, chazakah, you would not be
allowed to expand it all the way to four by four, that
would be too much. It has to retain one of the initial
dimensions when you expand.
Yeah. Could be the other dimension or it could be like...
Yeah, he says if it was החזיק רוחב טפח במשך ארבע, hechezik
rochav tefach be-meshech arba, if it is one טפח tefach wide and
four long, then החזיק ברוחב ארבע, hechezik be-rochav arba, you can expand
the width up to four. So that is the suggestion here that
if it is one by four you could expand it into four
by four after the חזקה chazakah was established. Because the assumption... so
this becomes now a very useful place, this already four by four
is
substantial. is a serious place. I could put something there. That's the
size of a large dinner plate or something like that. So at
that point, the point is that establishing the חזקה, Chazakah, the significance
is the one טפח Tefach and one טפח Tefach can lead you
to four טפחים. Tefachim. Okay. The גמרא Gemara continues: פחות מטפח אין
לו חזקה. Pachot mitefach ein lo chazakah. If it's smaller than a
טפח, Tefach, it doesn't create any חזקה Chazakah at all, because less
than a טפח Tefach is a space of no significance at all,
even in contrast in הלכות שבת, Hilchot Shabbat, the space of significance
is four by four. Here, less than one טפח Tefach is a
place of significance. So for property rights, we have a little bit
of a stricter standard. So פחות מטפח אין לו חזקה. Pachot mitefach
ein lo chazakah.
So the person who would have might object, he might object even
to the one because he
also knows the הלכה Halacha that it could expand to four. That
would really bother him. Right.
Exactly.
So
he has to be able to understand or recognize that even a
small protrusion could expand later if it's of a significant size. So
if it's too small, if it's less than one טפח, Tefach, you're
never going to have the right to expand it, so he'll never
have a problem that he has to object to because it's so
small. So the assumptions here work well for both parties, that is,
if it's large enough that you could expand it later, then the
objecting party retains the right to be able to object because of
those changes, because of that significance.
But really, it is air rights, right?
It's some kind of an air rights, yeah. But also, if he
wants to build an extension of his house here and there's this
ledge, he won't be able to do that either, something like that.
Correct. He can't, but he can't touch the חצר, Chatzer, he can't
touch the ground.
Correct, because the חצר Chatzer belongs to this owner. Exactly.
Okay. Good. So אמר רב הונא. Amar Rav Huna. Okay. לא שנו
אלא בעל הגג בבעל החצר. Lo shanu ela baal hagag b'baal hachatzer.
The משנה Mishnah was only taught in the context of בעל הגג
בבעל החצר, Baal hagag b'baal hachatzer, that is, the roof owner, that
is, the house owner building the ledge into the חצר Chatzer space.
אבל בעל החצר בבעל הגג יכול למחות. Aval baal hachatzer b'baal hagag
yachol limchot. If the חצר Chatzer owner here would build a ledge
on his house, right, what if this person decided to build a
ledge on somebody else's wall? Then of course he could object because
that's his wall. So it's like רבי דב Rabbi Dov is saying,
it's about the air rights. That is, if you own this property,
you can have a little bit of an extension that protrudes into
someone else's property. But if you own this yard, you're not allowed
to just build a ledge on somebody else's wall.
Although you could think that maybe you could.
That's why someone
has to say that.
You can't build it connected to the wall. You could build a
free-standing structure that's a ledge that's sort of its own thing. But
it can't be connected to someone else's wall because that's their wall.
Are you saying that you could actually build a structure adjacent to
the wall within a few inches and the height of whatever that
ledge would have been?
Because this is the yard. He can do whatever he wants in
his yard, right, more or less? Right, he could build whatever he
wants, he could build a whole building here.
How close to that wall can he come?
Within, what, four טפחים, Tefachim, right? And if it's trampled or not
trampled, and all that. Okay, fine. So, that's the discussion. So that's
רב הונא's Rav Huna position. So אבל בעל החצר בבעל הגג יכול
למחות. Aval baal hachatzer b'baal hagag yachol limchot. ורבי יהודה אמר, v'Rabbi
Yehuda amar, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees with רב הונא. Rav
Huna. רבי יהודה אמר Rabbi Yehuda amar אפילו בעל החצר בבעל הגג
אינו יכול למחות. afilu baal hachatzer b'baal hagag eino yachol limchot. The
בעל החצר baal hachatzer builds into the בעל הגג, baal hagag, that
is, if the חצר Chatzer owner had built the ledge, right, this
person built the ledge, then even according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
that would be okay. The בעל הגג, baal hagag, this house owner,
would not be able to object. Okay. So לימא בהיזק ראיה קמיפלגי,
Leima b'hezek re'iyah kamiflagi, maybe the מחלוקת machloket is about היזק ראיה,
hezek re'iyah, about privacy. דמר סבר שמי היזק. D'mar savar shemei hezek.
One says היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah counts as a real היזק. hezek.
That is, if you stand on the ledge, you're going to be
able to peep into somebody else's yard. So maybe that's why there's
a concern. ורבי יהודה v'Rabbi Yehuda maybe has a lower threshold of
what counts as היזק ראיה. hezek re'iyah. ומר סבר לאו שמי היזק.
u'mar savar lav shemei hezek. Maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't think
היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah counts. So no, דכולי עלמא שמי היזק. d'kulei
alma shemei hezek. Everyone agrees that היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah is a
problem. Everyone thinks that there's privacy rights. Okay. ושאני הכא דאמר ליה
לתשמישתא לא חזי. v'shani hacha d'amar lei l'tashmishta lo chazi. So you
would say if you have a very small ledge, it's just one
by four, right? What can you use it for? You can't really
put anything there. You could stand on it to hang something up.
So that's what he says. למאי חזי? L'mai chazi? What is it
suitable for? למיטלא בה מידי. L'mitala bah midi. You could hang something
on it. מהדרינן אפין ותלינן בה. Mehadreinan apin v'talainan bah. So then
fine, require him to turn facing backwards. So if you're standing on
the ledge, right, you can to put something up on your roof
that you should be looking this way so that you're not peeping
into somebody else's yard. Okay. ואידך אמר ליה זימנין דבעיתת. v'idach amar
lei zimnin d'ba'itet. So רב הונא Rav Huna will say no. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says this is fine, as long as you look
this way, it's not a problem of היזק ראיה. hezek re'iyah. So
even a small ledge, there could be no objection. רב הונא Rav
Huna will say no, even if you stand this way, sometimes you're
going to look the other way. If you turn around the other
way or you're shaky, it's a small ledge, then it would be
a problem. So in that case Rav Huna would object and say
that no, it still would be a problem of היזק ראייה Hezek
re'iyah even a small ledge. It's interesting of course that what we
were discussing, it seemed like more of a problem of the physical
property rights, the way the גמרא Gemara brings the opinions of Rav
Huna and Rav Yehuda, it sounds more like they're interested in bringing
it into the context of היזק ראייה Hezek re'iyah about the privacy,
visibility rights rather than the actual physical property rights. So it's an
interesting question how to interpret those positions.
So you know, if there's no issue of מעקה? ma'akeh?
It's too small. You only need a מעקה ma'akeh if it's four
אמות amot by four אמות amot on a rooftop. So there's a
מחלוקת machloket about מעקה, ma'akeh, the fundamental requirement in the תורה Torah
to build a מעקה, ma'akeh, the מצות עשה mitzvath asei has a
minimum size, just like a מזוזה mezuzah or just like anything else,
it's only required in a place that actually has requisite size, but
the מצות לא תעשה, mitzvath lo ta'asei, ולא תשים דמים בביתך, Velo
tasim damim beveitecha, you can't have a dangerous arrangement, a dangerous environment,
applies to all sorts of circumstances. You have to make sure to
ensure that whatever construction is built there, it has to be built
in a safe way. So obviously if this ledge is built in
a very narrow space, it has to be restricted in such a
way that only that people who know how to go there that
will, I mean again, this is only a few feet off of
the ground is different than if it's really from the roof,
from the rooftop directly, the rooftop or you're saying you want me
to adjust the picture
so it depends a little bit more, don't build a מעקה. ma'akeh.
In other words, what are they putting on the roof? There's already
something there.
They have figs on the roof, I don't
know,
they
have laundry,
yeah, raisins, it's attached to the wall to do, so it'd still
only be like a foot and a half, right?
Right, it's still, meaning it's only three inches wide and only a
foot and a half long or a foot long, it's
a foot long, something like that.
It can't become a full מרפסת. mirpaset. Exactly.
So the guy is not concerned that somebody might sit on it.
Right, his concern is more that the person will stand on it,
that you'll hang something on it, something like that. The concern, so
the גמרא's Gemara's concern is well, if you're standing on the ledge
to put something on the roof, then you're going to end up
peeping into your neighbor's yard. That's really the concern the גמרא Gemara
has,
obviously there could be other cases as well. Let's just at least
read the משנה, mishnah, maybe go a little bit further and we'll
pick up tomorrow. Tomorrow is the last דף daf of חזקת הבתים.
Chazkat Habatim. So after our, I think it's been about a month
in this פרק, perek, it's a very long פרק. perek. It's a
fantastic פרק. perek. So the משנה mishnah says: לא יפתח אדם חלונותיו
לחצר השותפין. Lo yiftach adam chalonotav lachatzar hashutafin. Okay. A person who
is is a partner, so we have we'll build a new house
here, okay? See, this is a good artistic day. Okay, I'm going
to keep taking the wrong one. Okay, so we have two partners
who share share a חצר, chatzer, okay?
So here's our here's our חצר chatzer and they're both have their
door into the חצר, chatzer, so this is a shared
חצר. chatzer. Okay, fine. So לא יפתח אדם חלונותיו לחצר השותפין. Lo
yiftach adam chalonotav lachatzar hashutafin. If the two partners have a joint
ownership in the חצר, chatzer, you can't make a window to peep
into the חצר chatzer because even though you have rights to the
חצר, chatzer, you're a joint owner, so's he, so's he. So you're
compromising his privacy by building an unauthorized window that's going to compromise
the privacy in in the jointly owned חצר. chatzer. So that's what
the משנה mishnah says. לקח בית בחצר אחרת, Lakach bayit b'chatzer acheret,
if you build bought a house in a different חצר, chatzer, that
is that the door doesn't open here, that is I have a
joint ownership in this חצר, chatzer, but my door opens to a
different חצר, chatzer,
then לקח בית בחצר אחרת לא יפתחנה לחצר השותפין. Lakach bayit b'chatzer
acheret lo yiftachena l'chatzar hashutafin. I'm also not allowed to build a
second entrance into the jointly owned חצר chatzer because again it impedes
even though I have ownership rights, I don't get to reduce my
neighbor's privacy rights. Okay. בנה עלייה על גבי ביתו, Bana aliyah al
gabei beito, if I build a second story on my house, very
nice renovations, okay, לא יפתחנה לחצר השותפין, Lo yiftachena l'chatzar hashutafin, I
cannot make the stairwell of the second floor apartment go into the
חצר, chatzer, the jointly owned חצר, chatzer, אלא אם רצה בונה את
החדר לפנים, ella im ratzah boneh et hacheder lifnim, I have to
build the
the stairwell indoors מביתו mibeito ובנה עלייה על גבי ביתו ופותחה לתוך
ביתו. ubana aliyah al gabei beito ufotachah letoch beito. I have to
build the stairwell inside the house and it has to go and
then it can go through my house. So again the same principle,
all three cases illustrating the same principle that is even if I
have a joint ownership in the חצר, chatzer, I'm not allowed to
build something that's going to increase the foot traffic or reduce the
privacy of the חצר chatzer for my partner who owns it with
me. has a joint ownership in the חצר. chatzer. So the גמרא
Gemara says, מאי איריא חצר השותפין? Mai irya chatzer hashutafin? What, why
is this relevant for a jointly owned חצר? chatzer? אפילו חצר חברו
נמי לא. Afilu chatzer chaveiro nami lo. You're not allowed to do
that for somebody else's חצר, chatzer, privately owned חצר, chatzer, obviously. So
the גמרא... Gemara...
right, right, the חידוש chiddush is...
it's a strange question.
It's a strange... it's a terrible question.
It's a terrible question. So
לאו בעיא קאמר לאו בעיא לחצר חברו דלא אבל לחצר השותפין דאמר
ליה סוף סוף הכא בבית איצטנועי מינאי ובחצר קמשמע לן דאמר ליה
עד האידנא בחצר הוה בעינא איצטנועי מינך השתא אפילו לבית נמי בעינא
איצטנועי מינך.
lo baya ka'amar lo baya lechatzer chaveiro de lo aval lechatzer hashutafin
de'amar lei sof sof hakaba'it itstenu'ei minai bachatzer kama shma lan de'amar
lei ad ha'idna bachatzer hava ba'ina itstenu'ei
minach hashta afilu lebayit nami ba'ina itstenu'ei minach. So he can say
no, no, no, that is, if it's a jointly owned חצר chatzer
originally I had really no thoroughfare through the I had no I
never went in this חצר chatzer so much. I own I own
it partially but I don't really go there. So the neighbor will
say okay originally I had to be private from you in in
my house, but in the חצר chatzer I was I was sort
of sorry that that if I knew you were going to come
into the חצר chatzer then I would have to be private or
whatever but normally I could assume that I had some privacy in
the חצר. chatzer. Now the only privacy he gets is really in
the house. So he's saying you've reduced the privacy rights. So even
though you have an ownership right because it's changed the agreement by
by increasing your foot traffic into this or increasing your even your
window to be able to look into the חצר chatzer that compromises
the agreement, that's something that fundamentally changed the partnership so that's going
to compromise their agreement, it's going to compromise the rights of the
other partner. Okay, so now we have a little bit of a
case. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: מעשה באדם אחד שפתח חלונותיו לחצר השותפין.
ma'aseh be'adam echad shepatach khalonotav lechatzer hashutafin. There was a case where
somebody didn't follow the משנה. Mishnah. Someone built a new window going
into a חצר chatzer that was jointly owned with his partner. Okay,
ובא לפני רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. uva lifnei Rabbi Yishmael Beribi Yose.
So the case came to Rabbi Yishmael the son of Rabbi Yose.
אמר לו החזקת בני החזקת. Amar lo hechzakta beni hechzakta. He said
you created a חזקה. chazakah. ובא לפני רבי חייא. uva lifnei Rabbi
Chiya.
The case came to Rabbi Chiya now why are they doing double
jeopardy for the same case they didn't like Rabbi Yishmael's פסק. psak.
So he came to Rabbi Chiya. אמר יגעת ופתחת יגע וסתום. Amar
yagata upatachta yiga vistom.
You worked so hard to open up the window, now you have
to work hard to close up the window again. So it sounds
like Rabbi Yishmael either doesn't hold of this principle from our משנה.
Mishnah. It's very common in fact that the משנה Mishnah being authored
primarily by students of Rabbi Akiva, that the משנה Mishnah retains a
מחלוקת machloket between that Rabbi Yishmael's opinion is not so well represented
in the משנה Mishnah and it may be that Rabbi Yishmael would
disagree and the opinion of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya much later רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya was a contemporary of רבי, Rebbe, so רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya much more in line with the Mishnayic tradition holds
seemingly holds by the position in the משנה. Mishnah. אמר רב נחמן,
Amar Rav Nachman, Rav Nachman now the אמורא Amora much later says:
ולסתום לאלתר הוי חזקה. velistom la'altar havei chazakah.
If you close up the window immediately, that becomes a חזקה. chazakah.
חזקה chazakah on whose part? On a part of this partner to
create a חזקה chazakah to be able to prevent any kind of
construction in the field, in the חצר chatzer שאין אדם עשוי שסותמין
אורו בפניו ושותק
she'ein adam asui shesotmim
oro befanav veshoteik
because people don't let you close up the window without permission. That
is the assumption here, that is it becomes too harsh the opposite
way. If he would have opened the window and then this partner
comes and blocks up the window again so that's not that's not
fair to him. He needs to have enough warning or enough time
to be able to deal with it.
Wait a minute, but that window was it being
blocked up jointly owned or not? The חצר chatzer is jointly owned,
this person decides to make a window that increases his to be
able to get some more light in his house or whatever but
because he's not allowed to do that so maybe this partner is
allowed to block up the window to board it up and the
response from רב נחמן Rav Nachman much later is yeah but technically
he's allowed because the window was built without permission. The problem is
now you've allowed this person to block up someone's light source very
quickly with no warning and with no process. So that's a reciprocal
problem that is even if this was built without permission to be
able to board it up so immediately is also unfair. So it's
kind of balancing both both sides of the argument. So we'll stop
there. I hope everyone has a wonderful...
kind of like two wrongs don't make a right.
Kind of like two wrongs don't make a right.